The Vi/Ex Editor, Part 2: Line-Mode Addresses

By Walter Alan Zintz.

Line-Mode Addressing
Addressing a Section of Text
Now You Try It
Coming Up Next

[Editor's note: We'll surround text to be typed with actual double quotes, like: enter: "vi file1". Of course, don't type the quotes unless so instructed. We'll use “balanced quotes” for all other purposes.]

Whenever you want to give an editor command that will operate on text that's already in the file you're editing--to delete some text, change lower-case letters to capitals, write to a file, etcetera--the editor needs to know what part of the file to go to work on. A few commands have their addresses built in, and most line-mode commands have default addresses that the editor will use if you don't give an address, but that still leaves a lot of occasions where you need to know how to give the editor an address and what address to give.

Many line-mode commands are almost identical to corresponding commands in visual mode; many more do similar things in different ways. Most of the benefit of these duplicative command sets comes from the totally different addressing styles of line and visual modes. The differing address concepts mean that an edit that would be difficult or impossible to do with one mode's available addresses can be a piece of cake with an address form found in the other mode.

Since I mention “line mode” so often, you may wonder whether there really is a separate mode for line editing. There surely is--instead of filling your screen with text from the file you're editing, this mode gives you a colon ( : ) prompt for your line mode commands, and prints only an occasional line from the file on your screen. The feel of this mode is very much like giving UNIX commands from your shell prompt. Few people work in line mode these days, largely because you can give most line-mode commands from visual mode, but you can't give any visual-mode commands while you are in line mode. Or perhaps they just prefer the comfortable WYSIWYG feeling of seeing the text on screen, with changes appearing as they are made.

But there are times when you will need to work temporarily in line mode. To get to line mode when you first launch the editor, invoke it by typing "ex" instead of "vi". To go to line mode when you are already in the editor's visual mode, enter "Q". To get back to visual mode, type "vi" followed by a carriage return.

Wondering why I didn't put a colon in front of that command to return to visual mode, which is obviously a line-mode command? Because you don't need to type that colon when you're giving a command from within line mode. It may even be harmful; the rule is that if you type a colon at the start of a command from within line mode, there must be nothing between the colon and the command name or abbreviation. Not an address, not even a space, nothing at all.

So from this point on, I will display line-mode commands without an initial colon, because you now know enough to type that colon only if you're working in visual mode. And I'll leave off the tag at the end of a line-mode command that reminds you to finish with a carriage return because you now realize that any line-mode command, given from either line or visual mode, has to end with a carriage return.

Some of you may ask why I show line-mode command lines in long-winded form, with spelled-out command names and lots of whitespace instead of using abbreviations. For instance, the two command lines:

global /^/ move 0
g/^/m0

are identical in their effect, and the second is surely faster to type, so why do I show the first form? Because the long version is much easier to follow when I'm demonstrating a new concept, and almost everything here will be new to at least some of you. And it's a good idea to get to know the long forms, because you'll soon be learning to write editor scripts, and those scripts would be as cryptic as APL to future maintenance programmers if you wrote them in terse style. When I go over the roster of line-mode commands, I'll tell you both the long name and one or two short names for each.

Line-Mode Addressing

A SINGLE ADDRESS is often all you need with a line-mode command. One address refers to just one line, which tells a command like delete or substitute to operate on that one line only. A command like insert or read, which puts something immediately before or after a particular line, has no use for more than one address.

A search pattern, as discussed in the first installment of this tutorial, is always an acceptable line-mode address. You put the address at the start of the command line, before the command name (but after the initial colon if you are giving the command from visual mode), so:

?the [cC]at? delete

will erase the last previous line that contains the string “the cat” or “the Cat”, while:

/^GLOSSARY$/ read gloss.book

puts the contents of the file “gloss.book” right after the next line in the file you're editing that contains only the word “GLOSSARY”.

There are two shorthand forms for reusing search patterns as addresses. Typing "??" or "//" tells the editor to use the last search pattern you used previously, and your choice of "??" or "//" will set the direction of the search, overriding the direction you chose the previous time you used that search pattern. That is, if you type:

?the cat? yank
// delete
?? print

the second command will search forward, to remove the last previous line containing the string “the cat”, even though your original use of that pattern was in a backward search. The third command will search backward to find the line to print, which (by coincidence) is the direction of the original search.

But the search pattern that those preceding abbreviations reuse may not be a pattern you used to search for a line. If you ran a substitute command after any pattern searches for lines, then the pattern you gave the substitute command to tell it what text to take out of the line is the pattern that will be reused. This is so even if your substitute command began with a search pattern to specify the line on which the substitution was to be performed--the search to find the pattern to be replaced within the line was run after the first search pattern had found the line to operate on, so the search within the line was the last pattern search run. So if you were to type:

/the cat/ substitute /in the hat/on the mat
?? delete

the second command would, in this case, delete the last previous line containing “in the hat”. To be sure that the pattern that gets reused is the last one used to find a line, use the abbreviations "\?" and "\/" to search backward and forward, respectively. In all other respects these work just as typing "??" and "//" do.

A LINE NUMBER is also a valid line-mode address. The editor automatically numbers each line in the file consecutively, and this numbering is dynamic--that is, whenever you add or delete lines somewhere, the editor renumbers all the lines following the insertion or deletion point. So if you change some text on line 46 in your file, and then delete lines 11 and 12, the line with the text you changed is now line 44. And if you then add ten new lines after line 17, the line with your changed text on it now automatically becomes line 54.

There is never a gap or an overlap in the line number sequence, so the nth line in the file is always line number n; that is, the 7th line is always line number 7, and so on. (There are several ways to display these line numbers, which I will expound in a later tutorial installment.) To delete the 153rd line in your file, just type:

153 delete

You don't use any delimiters around a line number, or around any other address except a search pattern.

There are two symbolic line numbers and one fictional one that can be used in line-mode addresses. As long as there are any lines in the buffer (that is, you haven't specified a not-yet-existent file to edit and failed to enter any text so far), the editor regards you as being `on' one of them, usually the last line affected by your latest command. A period or dot ( . ) is the symbolic address for this line. The last line in the file also has a symbolic address: the dollar sign ( $ ). So if you should type:

. write >> goodlines
$ delete

the first command would append a copy of just the line you are on now to a file named “goodlines”, while the second would delete the last line in the file you are editing.

A few commands put text immediately after the line address you give: the append command is one of them. In order to let them put their text at the very start of a file (if that is where you want it), these commands can take the fictitious line number zero (0) as their address. So, if you want to type some text that will appear ahead of anything already in the file, you can do it with either of these command lines:

1 insert
0 append

(Note, though, that insert and append are among the few line-mode commands that cannot be run from visual mode by starting with a colon, because they occupy more than one line including the text to be put in.)

WRITING YOUR OWN LINE ADDRESSES is possible, too. You can attach lower-case letters to lines as line addresses, and change the attachments whenever you like. You can even use a special address that is automatically attached to the last line you jumped off from.

There are ways to mark a particular line with a lower-case letter of the alphabet, and those ways differ between line and visual modes. I'll be explaining all these ways in later installments of this tutorial. But once a line is marked, the line-mode address that refers to that line is just the single-quote character followed immediately by the lower-case letter with which the line was marked. So typing:

'b print

will display on the screen whatever line you have previously marked with the letter b, no matter where the line is in relation to where you are when you give the command. No need to tell the editor whether to search forward or backward; there can be only one line at a time marked with any one letter, and the editor will find that line regardless.

The editor does some line marking on its own, too. Whenever you move from one line to another by a non-relative address, the editor marks the line you just left. (A non-relative address is one that isn't a known number of lines from where you were.) So:

$
/the cat/
358
?glossary? +7
'b

are all non-relative addresses, and if you give any one of them, the editor will mark the line you are leaving for future reference. Then you can return to that line just by typing two successive single quotes:

''

as a line-mode address. In theory, you can use this address with any line-mode command. But it is so difficult to know for sure when you left a line via a non-relative address that this address form is best saved for going back to where you were when a mistake moves you far away, at least until you're a wizard with this editor.

MODIFYING ANY OF THESE ADDRESSES is possible, and there are two ways to do this. The simpler way is to offset the address a certain number of lines forward or backward with plus ( + ) or minus ( - ) signs. The rule is that each plus sign following an address tells the editor to go one line farther forward in the file than the basic address, while each minus sign means a line backward. So these three addresses all refer to the same line:

35
37 --
30 +++++

Not that you're likely to want to modify line-number addresses with counts, unless you're weak in arithmetic and want the editor to do the adding and subtracting for you. But the count offsets will work with any line-mode addresses, and are most often used with search patterns. In any event, there is a shorthand for these counts, too. A plus or minus sign immediately followed by a number (single or multiple digits) is equivalent to a string of plus or minus signs equal to that number, so that these two addresses are the same:

/^register long/ ++++
/^register long/ +4

Take note that the “4” in the second example does not mean “line number 4”, as it would if it appeared by itself as an address. After a plus or minus sign, a number is a count forward or backward from where the primary address lands (or if there is no primary address before the count, from the line you are on when you run the command).

Note also that this is one of the few places in line-mode commands where you may not insert a blank space. The number must start in the very next character position after the plus or minus sign. If you violate this rule, the editor will uncomplainingly operate on some line that definitely is not the line you expected.

The second style of address modifier is used where you want to do a search that's complex. Let's say you want to go forward in the file to delete a line that starts with “WARNING!”, but not the first such line the editor would encounter; you want the second instance. Either of these command lines will do it:

/^WARNING!/ ; /^WARNING!/ delete
/^WARNING!/ ; // delete

A semicolon ( ; ) between two search patterns tells the editor to find the location of the first pattern in the usual way, then start searching from that location for the second pattern. In this case, the first search pattern turned up the first instance of a line starting with “WARNING!”, and the second search pattern led the editor on to the second instance.

A very significant point here is that this combination of two search patterns, either of which could be a line address in itself, does not tell the editor to delete two lines. The semicolon means that the first pattern is merely a way station, and that the single line found by the second search pattern is the only line to be deleted. In brief, what looks like addresses for two lines is actually only an address for one. (This is not what the official documentation for this editor says, but the documentation is just plain wrong on this point.)

But that's just the start of what you can do. You are not restricted to just two addresses. I've used up to ten of them, all separated by semicolons, to reach one specific line. As an example:

?^Chapter 3$? ; /^Bibliography$/ ; /^Spinoza/ ; /Monads/

will bring me to the title line of Spinoza's first work with “Monads” in the title, in the bibliography for Chapter 3.

Nor are you limited to search pattern addresses when putting together a semicolon-separated address string. If you want to reach the first line following line 462 that contains the word “union”, typing:

462 ; /\<union\>/

will bring you there. And any of the addresses can take numerical offsets, so:

462 +137 ; /register int/ ---

is also a legitimate address string.

But there are two unfortunate limitations on using semicolon-separated address strings. The lesser problem is that such a string can use “line zero” as an address only if the command following the address string could take line zero by itself as its address. That is, you can't even start at line zero and then proceed elsewhere with additional addresses, unless the command can operate from line zero. So:

0 ; /Spinoza/ +++ ; /Kant/ delete

which looks like a reasonable way to be sure your search will find the very first “Spinoza” in your file, will actually fail with an error message about an illegal address.

The larger misfortune is that each address in a semicolon-separated string must be farther down in the file than the one that precedes it. (This means the actual location found, after applying any plus-sign or minus-sign offset.) You cannot move backward within the series of way points.

But that does not mean that you cannot use a backward search pattern within the string. The first address can be a backward search, of course. And a subsequent address can search backward if you are certain that the line it finds will actually be more forward in the file. For example, you may know that a certain backward search will wrap around to the bottom end of the file before it finds a match. A common example would be:

1 ; ?Spinoza? ; /Hegel/ yank

Beginning a backward search from the first line in the file means that the search must start with the last line in the file due to wraparound, which guarantees that the search will yank the “Hegel” line that follows the vary last “Spinoza” line in your file.

Also, you can use a plus-sign offset after a backward search when you are certain that the line finally found after the offset is applied will be farther down in the file than the preceding way point had been. Thus, if I want to find the first mention of Hegel in Chapter 8 that is at least 120 lines after the last mention of him in Chapter 7, I can type:

/^Chapter 8$/ ; ?Hegel? +119 ; //

If a command with this address fails and gives an error message about a bad address, I'll know that the last mention of Hegel in Chapter 7 is more than 120 lines before the end of the chapter, so the very first mention of his name in Chapter 8 is what I'm looking for. In that case, the address:

/^Chapter 8$/ ; /Hegel/

is all that my command needs.

The situation with forward searches inside a semicolon-separated address string is a mirror image of what I've just said. A forward search can take a minus-sign offset if you know that the offset is small enough that the line found will be further down than the last way point. But a forward search will fail, even with no offset or a plus-sign offset, if wraparound makes it find a line earlier in the file than the way point from which it began.

Addressing a Section of Text

TWO ADDRESSES CAN ALSO STAND FOR A RANGE OF LINES. When two addresses are separated by a comma rather than a semicolon, the meaning changes radically. (What a difference a dot makes!)

Often you will want a line-mode command to act on a series of successive lines. For example, you may want to move a stretch of text from one place to another. To do this, you give the address of the first line you want the command to act on, followed by the last line it should act on, and separate the two addresses with a comma. So, the command:

14 , 17 delete

will delete line 14 and line 15 and line 16 and line 17. You can see that putting more than two addresses in a comma-separated address string would be pointless. The line mode of this editor is discreet if you ignore this and string together three or more addresses with comma separation: it uses the first two addresses and discards the rest.

Any line-mode addresses may be used with a comma. All of the following combinations make sense:

'd , /^struct/
257 , .
?^Chapter 9$? , $

The first address combination would cause the command that follows it to operate on the section starting with the line you have previously marked “d” and ending with the next forward line that begins with “struct”, inclusive. The second combination covers line 257 through the line you are on now. The third goes backward to include the previous line containing only “Chapter 9”, and forward to include the very last line in your file; plus all the lines in between, of course.

There are limitations on this technique, too. The primary one is that the address after the comma (after any offsets, of course) cannot be earlier in the file than the address before the comma. That is, the range of lines must run forward from the first address to the second address. So the command:

57 , 188 delete

is just fine, while the similar-looking command:

188 , 57 delete

will only produce an error message. (But if the two addresses happen to evaluate to the same line, there is no problem. The command will silently operate on the one line you've specified.)

As you work up to more sophisticated line-mode addresses, you may get unexpected error messages about the second address being prior to first address, when you don't see how you could have anticipated that the addresses would evaluate that way. That's no disgrace, and the solution is simple. After you've looked over the addresses you used, and you're certain that they are the ones you want, just type the command in again with the two addresses in reverse order. That is, if:

642 , /in Table 23/ delete

has failed, giving an error message that the lines are in the wrong order, then:

/in Table 23/ , 642 delete

will solve that problem.

The last limitation is that when you use search patterns on both sides of a comma, the second search starts from the current line just as the first search did; it does no t start from the line that the first search found. There's a way around that, though, that involves using one or more semicolons along with a comma.

A semicolon-separated address string can be used anywhere in line mode that you would use a single address. One very useful technique is to use these address strings on one or both sides of a comma, to indicate a range of lines to be affected. Remember that an address string separated by semicolons is the address of just one line, so this one line can be the start or the end of a range of lines. For example, in:

/^INDEX$/ ; /^Xerxes/ , $ write tailfile
?^PREFACE$? ; /^My 7th point/ , ?^PREFACE$? ; /^In summary/ -- delete

the first command would write the latter part of the index to a new file, while the second could be used to remove a section of a book's preface.

And that brings up the solution to our previous obstacle; the second search's starting point. If you want the search after the comma to begin f rom the point the first search found, use the first search pattern followed by a semicolon as the start of your after-the-comma search string, as in either of:

?Stradivarius? , ?Stradivarius? ; /Guarnerius/
?Stradivarius? , ?? ; /Guarnerius/

In view of the rules about not going backward in line-mode address strings, I'd better clarify the way these limitations work when you combine semicolon and comma separation, as in these two examples. All but the first of the way points in each semicolon-separated string must be in the forward direction, of course, but the start of the second semicolon-separated string may be prior to any of the addresses in the first such string, that is, the one-way meter resets itself at the comma point. And using semicolon-separated strings on both sides of a comma only requires that the final landing point of the second semicolon-separated string not be earlier in the file than the final landing point of the first; the relative locations of t he way points don't matter to the comma. To clarify this, consider a couple of odd-looking, and useless, but very lucid examples. The combination:

125 ; 176 ; 221 , 32 ; 67 ; 240

looks invalid due to the backward jump from line 221 to line 32, but is actually a perfectly good address. The back jump comes right after the comma, where it is all right. But:

125 ; 176 ; 221 , 32 ; 67 ; 218

will produce an error message, because the final landing point of the first semicolon-separated string, line 221, falls later in the file than the final landing point of the second semicolon-separated string, line 218.

Now, a note about default addresses. I've already mentioned that most line-mode commands that can take an address have a “default” address built in, which tells the editor where to run the command if you don't give an address with it. Each command has its own default address, which may be the current line, the current li ne plus the one following, the last line of the file, or the entire file.

The comma separator has default addresses of its own. They are the same regardless of what command is being used, and they override any command's own default address. If you put a comma before a command and don't put an address before the comma, by default the address there is the current line. In the same way, if you leave out the address after the comma, the default there is also the current line. You can even leave out the address in both places and use the current-line default in both: that means the implied address is “from the current line to the current line”, which makes the current line the only line the command will operate on. So every one of the following command lines:

.     write >> goodlines
. , . write >> goodlines
  , . write >> goodlines
. ,   write >> goodlines
  ,   write >> goodlines

will do exactly the same thing: append a copy of j ust the current line in the file you're editing to another file named “goodlines”.

Finally, there is one special symbol that represents a comma-separated address combination. The percent sign ( % ) has the same meaning as 1,$ as a line-mode address combination. Both refer to the entire file.

Now You Try It

Before you try the complex aspects of line-mode addresses in actual editing situations, here are some problems you can build yourself up on. For each problem I've included a solution that will work fairly efficiently.

How can you tell the editor to delete the line that holds the very last instance of “EXPORT” in your file? The solution is straightforward once you know where to start searching.

Suppose you want to delete the very first line in the file with “EXPORT” on it, and that just might be line 1. You can't start the search from line zero because the delete command cannot take line 0 as an address. When you type the address string "$ ; /EXPORT/" to use wraparound, you get an error message asserting that the search pattern found a line prior to the line found by the “$” address that appeared first, which is what you'd expect. How can you tell the editor to find and delete this line? The solution requires just a bit of creativity.

If you use the address "?abc? , /xyz/" , it includes the two lines the searches (for “abc” and “xyx”) find, as well as all the lines between them. How would you specify that you want the affected lines to go up to, but not include, the lines the two searches find? In this case the solution is simpler than you might think.

Coming Up Next

The next installment of this tutorial will deal with the Global commands--they're ju st too much to absorb right after the mind-numbing collection of address forms we've just gone through. And to give you more scope for using all these address forms, I'll also cover line-mode commands themselves, particularly the ones that have more capabilities than you suspect.

Take Charge with Macros

By Walter Alan Zintz .

Text-Insertion Macros

What These Tools Do
Working Principles

Command-Submode Macros

:map Macros
Buffer Macros
:source Macros
Write and Read Macros

In The Next Installment of this Tutorial
SIDEBAR: The timeout Function

Text-Insertion Macros

As befits an editor with all those built-in metacharacters that operate while you are typing in text, there are two ways to create your own macros for use during text insertion. Both can be useful in the right circumstances, so you'll probably want to put them to work at times. You may not have a choice -- often the .exrc file that you may be given when you get a new Unix shell account has some of these shorthand dodges built in. These two tools have as many similarities as differences, so I will expound them in parallel.

What These Tools Do

Both tools act only when you are in text-insertion submode of screen-editing mode. Nonetheless, the commands that set them up and manage them are line-mode commands like:

:ab ucb University of California at Berkeley
:map! } Control-[k2cc

The two example lines above will set up two shorthand forms that you can use without further preliminaries. The first line provides that whenever you type ``ucb'' as a separate word in your text, the editor will replace it with ``University of California at Berkeley''. It happens right on the spot, and without any special signal from you.

The second line is for use if you frequently discover that what you are typing has become a mess, and that the mess started back on the previous line. With this shorthand form in effect, whenever there is a ``}'' character in what you type in, the editor removes it and instead acts as if you had typed in ``Control-[k2cc''. That is, the Control-[ (generate d by the ``Escape'' key on your keyboard) causes the editor to escape from text-insertion to command mode, the ``k'' causes the cursor to move up a line, and the ``2cc'' removes both of the lines involved and puts you back in text-insertion mode, ready to type in a replacement for those lines and continue on with your text insertion. As with the previous tool, this happens as soon as you type in the shorthand form, without any special action by you.

Note that whitespace separates either of these setup commands into three parts. The first part, from the start of the line up to the first stretch of whitespace, is just the command name. Part two, between the first and second stretches of whitespace, is the short form that you will type into the text. The third part, everything following the second stretch of whitespace, is what the editor will insert (and/or execute) when you type in the short form. Only the first two stretches of whitespace are separators -- any later stretches are integral componen ts of part three. And whitespace includes both space characters and tabs, in any mixture.

Working Principles

Now that you've seen what these two tools do, let's consider how they work:

:abbreviate

(Shortest abbreviation is :ab ). This tool acts when you type in a certain character or string as a separate word, each end bounded by whitespace, or a punctuation character, or the start or end of a line, or the start or end of an insertion. As soon as the editor sees that the abbreviation is a word by itself, it replaces that abbreviation with the longer word or phrase you have set as equivalent.

As an example, you might have declared ``cat'' as your abbreviation for ``felix domesticus''. Then, wherever you type in a line such as ``the habits of the common cat include'', the editor will promptly change it to read ``the habits of the common felix domesticus include''. But there will be n o such change in words that happen to include the string ``cat'' in them, such as ``catamaran'' or ``concatenation''. Be careful with this, because while the word ``catlike'' will not be changed, the word ``cat- like'' will be.

Neither a backslash (\) nor a control-V will quote an abbreviation into a file as itself. Usually, the easiest way to insert an abbreviation into your text is to escape from text-insertion submode (back to command submode) in the middle of typing the abbreviation, then re-enter text-insertion submode and type in the rest of the abbreviation. If your abbreviation is only one character long, though, you must fall back on typing the abbreviation with a letter immediately before or after it, then returning to command submode to erase the unwanted extra letter.

:map!

(No editor-accepted abbreviation). Very similar to the abbreviation tool discussed above, but with three major differences:

The shorthand form defined wi th this command does not need to be typed into your inserted text as a separate word in order to operate. Even if it is embedded within another word, the short form will disappear and its related text will be entered in its place.
This tool does not simply insert the related text into the file, as the :abbreviate tool does; it acts as though the user had typed in the related text instead of the short form. That is, if there is an escape character in the related text, that escape will put the editor back into command submode, and interpret any following characters as screen-mode commands. (Unless one of those characters returns you to text insertion submode -- then characters following that insert-text command will be all be put into the file, unless and until there is another escape character.) That makes accidentally triggering this tool rather dangerous.
Quoting in a character or string that you've defined as a short form via this command is simple. Typ e control-V before the metacharacter, or the first character of the metastring, and into the text it goes. Even that may not be required if you are dealing with a metastring, and if the timeout option to the :set command is still in its default state: turned on. In this case, all you need to do is be sure that you take more than one full second to type in the entire metastring, and it will have no meta effect. (This, by the way, is one reason that this tool's metastrings should be short -- so you can depend on being able to type one of them in less than a full second when you do want the metavalue.)

Questions naturally arise regarding these tools. One frequent query is why anyone would want to mess around with :abbreviate when it seems much easier to do a general substitution command when the document is complete. That is, instead of that abbreviation I set up at the start of this explanat ion, just run a :%s/\<ucb\>/University of California at Berkeley/g command after all the text has been entered. There are several reasons to use Vi's abbreviation feature instead:

It's not hard to unknowingly type in your abbreviated string where you don't want it expanded, as in a direct quotation (Savio told the students, ``We don't want ucb to get the upper hand!''), or where it has an entirely different meaning (Next, punch in the code: aQr PxN ucb JHt.) Using the substitution command above, you would never see that these sentences were being disfigured. But with on-the-spot replacement the mistaken use would be right in your face.
Lines can get very long when abbreviations are expanded, especially when there are several abbreviations in one line. When you use a general substitution command after text entry, there's no way to know that certain lines have become unreasonably long. But with the :abbreviate tool, yo u see the final length of each line as you go along. And if you use the wrapmargin option to the :set command, line breaks will generally be inserted after any abbreviations have been expanded.
It's easy to forget to run a general substitution command. But a :abbreviate command can be made automatic by putting it in a .exrc file, and the user can see while typing whether it is or is not in operation.
This tool can do more than save typing. For example, suppose a technical writer is in the habit of typing ``unix'', while company policy requires ``UNIX(R)''. Either a general substitution or the :abbreviate tool will correct that writer's recurring errors, but only the latter will continuously teach him that ``unix'' is not to be used. As another example, consider a writer who begins far too many sentences with the word ``The'', which makes for dull reading. A :a b The DON'T OVERDO IT! command will ensure that every time this writer types the word ``The'' at the start of the sentence, it will promptly be transmuted into the billboard phrase ``DON'T OVERDO IT!'', which can be backspaced over to insert a new sentence beginning. Note that this will not be triggered by words such as ``These'' or ``Then'', nor by the word ``the'' in the middle of a sentence.

Another common question concerns precedence of metacharacters. You can use most of the text-input metacharacters I've discussed previously as short-form names in :map! commands. Suppose you did use control-D as such a short form -- what would happen when you typed control-D at the start of an autoindented line? Would it wipe out the indentation or type in the phrase that :map! has associated with it? Or if you used control-H as a short form? When you subsequently typed a control-H during text entry, would the cursor back up a space, or would type in a stored phrase?

The answer is that the :map! value would prevail. By preceding either character with a control-V, you could type in in as itself, but there would be no way to use the ordinary metavalue of either character. If you were to map control-D followed immediately by another control-D or two consecutive control-H characters or any other doubling of an ordinary metacharacter, the situation would be more complex. You could then type the two control-D or control-Hs within one second to get the mapped text typed in, or you could type control-D or control-H followed by a one-second pause to invoke the ordinary metavalue.

Time for another exercise .
Suppose that you used control-D or control-H as a short form with the :abbreviate command. Or suppose that you used some ordinary character string as both an abbreviation and a mapping short form. (The editor will allow you to do this.) What would happen when you typed in this double-use short form during text insertion? This exercise is straightforward enough that I expect most of you will find the correct answer before you look at my solution .

Two final warnings. Do not try to define a non-alphanumeric character or string as a short form with the :abbreviate command. You probably will be able to do this -- the editor won't object -- but when you try to use this abbreviation, nothing will happen. And with either :abbreviate or :map! , do not put any metacharacter as itself into the long-form string. Even if you manage to get it into the string as itself, it will not go into your text that way.

What if you have forgotten what short forms you have set up, or are uncertain as to whether some may have been set up for you via a .exrc startup file? Well, you can query either tool ju st by giving its setup command without any arguments. Here are examples of those queries, with the responses you might receive from the editor:

:ab

cat   cat   felix domesticus
wolf  wolf  canis lupus


:map!

{     {     ^[o^I^IThe End^[
}     }     ^[o^I^I-XXX-^[
~     ~     (more to come)^[

Note that each response line has at least three strings of printing characters, separated by whitespace. It's that second string in a line that is the short form; the string that when typed in will be replaced by the last string shown. (Yes, in every example line above the first string is identical to the second, but that isn't always so.) The last string is what will be inserted and/or executed.

So now you know what characters and strings will have to be quoted in when you want to insert them as themselves. And if one or more of those short forms is something you will be typing in so often that you can't spare the time to quote it in each time you use i t, you can disable the metavalue for the rest of the present editing session. Just give the command name for the tool that uses this short form but precede it with ``un'', and as the only argument give the short form you want to disable. For example, here are the commands that will disable the first entry in each of the lists above:

:unab cat
:unmap! {

Command-Submode Macros

It's common that a text editor has a facility that lets a user create personalized commands, usually as macros built on existing commands. The Vi/Ex editor has four such facilities -- something for every need. While these facilities don't have the low-level programmability of mock-Lisp, they can accomplish a lot to simplify your editing, and you don't need to learn a programming language to use them.

I'll be discussing each facility (or family) in its own section below, because their structures are quite different. Nonetheless, you can often combine them to go od effect, by using a macro of one type to call a macro of a different type.

:map Macros

This is the editor tool that's closest to what most users think of as a macro facility. It uses the command :map as its setup tool, and the macros it creates operate when the user is in command submode of screen-editing mode. Otherwise it works just the way its very close relative, the :map! tool, works -- which I explained in depth in the first half of this tutorial part, above. Consider the three command lines below:

:map v :!wc -w %Control-M
:unmap v
:map

The first line sets up a macro that does a word count on the file I am editing, as of the last write to storage, whenever I type the letter v from command submode while I am screen editing. The second unsets that macro, so that a v command no longer does anything. The third displays a list of the :map macros that are currently in effect. All this should be transparently plain to readers who understand the :map! tool. Still, there are a few points worth noting that are particularly applicable to the :map side of the family.

Choosing a short-form for :map macros should not be difficult. Half a dozen of the printing ASCII characters and many of the control characters are not used as screen-editing commands or addresses. Hardly any strings of two duplicate characters (such as ``DD'' above) are in use, and most editor versions will let you map such strings. You don't need to avoid duplicating your :map! short forms because the name spaces are completely separate. That is, if you use a particular character or string as a :map short-form and also as a :map! short-form; for example:

:map }} :!wc -w %Control-M
:map! }} Control-[j0R

there is no conflict. The editor will allow both mappings, and will use the correct long-form based on the context; whether you typed }} from command or text-insertion submode. As the first example above shows, your command string can include any of the line-mode commands that can be invoked from screen mode, providing you begin each one with a colon ``:'' as you would when invoking it directly while in screen mode, and quote in a Control-M (the RETURN character) to terminate the command.

Suppose that you ran the two following setup commands, either one first:

:map Q 2dd
:map V 3jQ

The first command clearly provides that the Q command, which ordinarily is the command that takes you out of screen mode and into line mode, does not do that any more. Instead, it now deletes two lines, and you now have no way to leave screen mode without unmapping the ``Q'' c haracter. But what does the new V do?

If you've left the :set command's remap option turned on, its default value, then the V drops down three lines and then deletes that third line and the one following. That is, when it comes to the ``Q'' character in that mapping, it discovers that ``Q'' itself has been mapped, and brings in the mapped value of ``Q''. But if you had previously run a :se noremap command, then the editor would not check for any mappings of the characters within a macro, and would use the standard meaning of ``Q'' when it executed the ``V'' macro. So then typing a ``V'' character would move you down three lines and then put you into line-editing mode. (Yes, that means that while you would no longer be able to execute the Q as itself directly, your macros could still access it!)

Buffer Macros

There are limits to the amount of macro text you can store by mapping it -- not as severe now as with earlier versions of the editor, but still somewhat confining. To remedy that, the editor offers a quite-similar tool with practically unlimited storage. It involves those buffers where you store text pulled from your file, for later reinsertion at various places. Specifically I mean the twenty-six buffers named ``a'' through ``z''.

From screen-editing command sub-mode, you can type an at-sign ``@'' followed by a letter of the alphabet, and the editor will take the contents of the buffer with that letter-name and execute it as a screen-mode command string. For example, if you have ``0d3w'' (without the quotation marks) stored in named-buffer ``k'', then typing @k will delete the first three words on the current line. After you start using this method in your editing session, there's an extra added convenience available: typing @@ wi ll repeat the last such buffer command you ran.

To put a command into a named buffer, get the line or lines of your command into your file one way or another, then delete or yank them into the buffer of your choice, as by:

"p3dd
:ya m

to delete a three-line macro into buffer ``p'' and yank a one-line macro into buffer ``m'', respectively. You need not tell the editor that you regard the contents of a buffer as a command macro until you choose to execute it with a ``@'' command. In fact, you can use a buffer's contents both ways, executing it as a command at one moment and putting it back into your file as text the next.

One important difference from macros created by mapping: if you need a linebreak character in a buffer macro, don't try to quote it in. Instead, type it in the ordinary way, so that it forms a line break between two lines of your macro text. And don't break a line in your macro text for any other reason, because the linebreak characte r that appears there will be treated as a command character by the editor when you execute the buffer contents as an editing command string.

:source Macros

Line-mode commands have a macro tool in this editor, too. Of course you can insert most line-mode commands in the previous two types of macros, but this tool is dedicated entirely to line-mode commands, and can include even commands that can't be run interactively from screen mode via a preceding colon. The only line-mode commands that can't be run with this tool are the visual and open commands. With this tool, you set up your macros by putting their commands into one or more files, then invoke them with command lines like:

:so /u/myname/commands.1

Your command files should contain strictly line-mode commands, one per line unless you separate them within the line by pipe ``|'' characters, a nd should not have a colon before each command. The other restrictions depend on how you plan to invoke your macro files. Ideally you should give your source commands while you are in line mode -- then the above limitations are all you will face. But if you insist on invoking :source while in screen mode, there are two other limitations:

Only the first line of your command file will execute. Due to the editor restriction against running multi-line line-mode commands while in screen mode, all lines after the first in your command file will be silently discarded.
If your first command is not complete on the first line (for instance, an append is not), even that command will not execute. In this case the failure will not be silent.

Another Exercise
So if you want to source in command files from within screen mode, it's a very good idea to create one-line com mand files. But there will be a few cases where multi-line command files will be a worthwhile thing, even when you may be invoking them from screen mode. Here's an easy exercise for you: come up with a specific case in which a command file that you may source in from either line or screen mode should nonetheless have more than one line. Of course there are multiple possibilities here, so don't be disturbed if the solution that occurs to you is not one of those I arbitrarily chose for my answer .

When you really get into sourcing, you'll be pleased to know that :source files can contain commands to call other :source files. This is the basis for truly modular editor scripts, and for a raft of rather tricky maneuvers. It also saves typing when you need to invoke a source file from screen mode, but the list of commands is simply too long to fit on one line: a single line in your initial source file is lo ng enough to call a very large number of other source files, each with a single long line of commands. You will probably find that invoking nested :source files from line mode will turn off line mode's colon prompt, but you can turn it back on again via a :se prompt command.

Write and Read Macros

The Vi/Ex editor has tools for running some or all of the lines in the file you're editing through a program outside the editor, then using the transformed lines to replace the original lines in your file. It can also run a program with any or no input and insert the program's output in your file, or write some or all of your file lines as input to a program that may send its output anywhere.

And where is the macro capability in all this? Well, when you use these tools you are not limited to standard Unix utilities as your outside programs -- your own coding will do just as well. Compiled or scripted, one line or a thousand, in a standard language like C or Perl or in a specialized one such as Snobol; the rule is that if your Unix system will execute it, the editor can pass it over your text.

This tutorial is not going to get into writing these personal text processors, in any language, so I will only be explaining how to send your text in and/or out via editor tools. In the examples below, I will suppose you have a text-processing program named myhack that lives within your searchpath.

[ Editor's note : One external program I use frequently reformats paragraphs into nicely looking text blocks that are easier to read. I use the program named reform , published on pages 320-321 in the first edition of the famous book

Programming Perl

by Larry Wall and Randal L. Schwartz. At first blush you may ask, why use such an external program when I can simply set Vi's wrapmargin variable? Of course, the answer is how do you easily reform paragraphs that are alre ady ragged, say due to the problem Walter posed above (using find and replace to expand abbreviations, instead of expanding abbreviations using the built-in Vi abbreviation macro facility?]

Note that the command to execute the outside program should be typed as you would type it at your shell prompt, because it will be passed to the shell intact except for the addition of input and/or output redirection.

If you want to take some (or all) of the lines out of your file, use them as input to your outside program, then put the resulting output in place of the original lines, you can use either a line-mode or a screen-mode command to do it, as shown below:

:196,254 ! myhack -n6
!L myhack -n6
12!! myhack -n6
!/^CHAPTER/- myhack -n6

The line-mode command can be invoked from line mode, or from screen mode by preceding it with a colon. In either case, you give an address or address range, next the exclamation point, then everything following until you type return is passed to the shell as a command line. The line-mode command must have at least one address because there is no default address for this command. But the whitespace I show before and after the exclamation point is permissible but not necessary; I put it in solely for readability.

Screen-mode command form is the exclamation point as the command name, followed by the target address, then the outside command (with arguments and/or whitespace as would be required or permitted on your shell command line), ending when you hit the escape or return key. As with the c d y commands, you can type two consecutive exclamation points to send just the current line, and use a count to send that number of lines as shown in my third example command. The last example involves an extra escape character -- at the end of a search pattern address, whether / or ? based and including any + or - suffix, you must press the escape key before you start typing the outside command.

You' re not limited to just one outside program at a time. You can pipeline two or more together as your shell permits, ordinarily with the ``|'' character. (Because a | character and what follows it will be passed to the shell, this editor command cannot appear in a line-mode command string, including a :global string, unless it is the last command in the string.) The final output of the pipeline is what will go into your file. And you can undo the effect of the outside command or pipeline, putting your file back the way it was, with a u command.

You may not want your text to make a round trip, though. You may want to send your text, as modified by your outside program, off to some other destination, or you may want to pull some text into your file that originated in your outside program, or was taken from some outside source. In these cases, use the line-mode commands that appear below:

:1,.w ! myhack -n6 > nufile
:2
17r ! myhack -n6 < oldfile

The first command above sends the initial lines from the file you are editing as input to your myhack program, and redirects the output to a file. It does not erase the affected lines from the file you are editing. The second runs your myhack program using the contents of another file as the input, then places the output in the file you are editing, right after line 217.

Both line-mode commands are shown with addresses, but they are not necessary. The default address for a :write command is the entire file; for a :read command, right after the current line. The space character just before the exclamation-point flag after each command is absolutely essential; without it you would get something greatly different from what you expected.

Usually there will be output redirection for the :write ! command, and input redirection for the :read ! command, but not always. For example, you may want to :read ! an outside command that generates a pseudo-random number, using no input at all. When you do need input or output, you can build the necessary redirection into your outside program or you can put the redirection on the command line as shown above, using your own shell's notation.

In The Next Installment of this Tutorial

I'll be putting the techniques I've taught so far to work, showing how to set up the editor for special purposes. Your suggestions on what special purposes to consider are welcome, of course. One purpose that is already in my mind is an arrangement of the editor for computerphobes: very simple, with beginner features such as ``stateless'' editing, and fortified against common user errors.

SIDEBAR: The timeout Function

The :set command's timeout option seems arcane in purpose and tricky to use, at least to some editor users. But it becomes pretty plain when you know why and how it actually works.

Basically, when the timeout option is on (its default state) and you type in a short form you've set up by a :map or :map! command, you must type the entire short form in no more than one second. If you miss that deadline, the editor will ignore the metavalue, and take the characters you've typed at their face value.

This odd requirement serves a purpose; preventing deadlock. As an example, suppose you have defined ``DD'' (without the quotation marks) as a macro via the :map command, and have turned off the timeout option. Now, while editing, you type a plain D command to delete part of a line. When the editor receives this single ``D'' it is uncertain what to do. Ar e you actually telling it to delete that partial line? Or are you starting to type in your double-D macro? The only way the editor can resolve this question is to wait and see what character you type in next. But if you are waiting to see the result of your deletion before you do any more editing, the mutual wait will last indefinitely. With the timeout option left turned on, the wait will only be a second or so before the editor acts on your D command.

One moral of this story is to leave timeout on unless you have a compelling reason to turn it off, and choose your macro names so that you can easily type them in within the one-second limit. If you are not particularly nimble fingered, or if other people may be using your editor macros, then for practical purposes this means either a single character or two repetitions of one character as in my example above. (Some fussy versions of the editor will refuse to map anything except a single character.)

Another moral is to avoid certain macro names, such as ``jj'' (again, without the quotation marks). The standard address j is one that you might want to type twice in rapid succession, to move directly down two lines without the trouble of reaching away from the central keyboard to hit the 2 key. But the user with a macro named jj had better not move down too quickly via that method, or he/she will accidentally invoke the macro of that name.

Finally, you should realize that the one-second count before timing out is not hair-splittingly accurate. The design of the standard Unix software clock means that the time-out interval may be a little less or somewhat more than precisely one second.